[music]
>> Welcome to 2026 release wave one, the
launch edition of Business Central where
in this session we're going to talk
about enhanced document reporting. My
name is Kenny Pontevedra and with me I'm
very proud to present Mirko. Hi, I'm
Mirko. I'm part of the engineering team
and today I will show you some of the
nice improvements we made to the word
add-in.
Cool.
Before we do that, let's just talk about
the value of these investments. So, at
least I could spot four.
The more effective ways to design your
document reports. You're going to see a
lot more of that in this space for the
next few years, so stay tuned.
Little spoiler alert. More effective
document layout management in general,
easier support for multi-language
companies and finally opening up with
APIs for different document types.
And so we're going to take you through
this from an updated word add-in all the
way down to APIs.
And
the first is our updated word add-in.
So,
the reason we wanted to invest in this
is simply to have the user experience
just much better on the data picker and
things related to designs. Why? Because
with word the intention is that it's not
going to be all developers who create
layouts for documents. It's more
moving towards um an office worker that
use word to do that and that means we
need to put the design experience in the
hands of users. We also need to invest
much more into the usability of things.
Sorry developers, but that's the way it
is. So, to demo the three new things,
enhanced UX for the data picker, search
in the data picker and a preview feature
of a table builder, let's see this in
action. Mirko, over to you.
All right, thank you Kenny. So, since
last time we released a data picker, we
collected tons of valuable feedback from
partners and customers.
So, let me show you how we use this
feedback to improve the user experience.
Right here, we have a simple customer
order summary layout which you can
download from Business Central.
And as you can see on the right side, we
have the new version of the data picker.
At first look, we can see that we now
have the our loved BC theme.
But more importantly, it is now easier
to navigate through all the data items.
It is easier to see the nested levels.
And
if we are in the document, we can now
insert a data item by simply double
clicking on it.
And even more nicely, if we are inside a
table like in this case,
whenever we insert a data item,
the cursor automatically moves to the
next cell, making the whole experience
smoother and faster.
We also have a new
icons here both for inserting and a new
show metadata action.
And when we click on it, this opens up a
pop-up which summarizes all the
meaningful information for the specific
data item.
And finally, we have a new filter
section here. So, if we are dealing with
a very long data set like this case,
we can now filter by simply typing in
the search bar.
So, let's say for example I'm looking
for something related to date.
All I need to do is to type
and then here I will have all the
related fields that are matching my
query across all the different levels
and labels, report information and so
on.
And if you are one of those that loves
dark mode, now we got you covered.
And there you go. You can now enjoy the
dark mode in the data picker.
All these new features will be available
in both the preview version and the
release version of the word add-in.
But we have something more because we
want to make the experience easier for
everybody and that's why in preview we
are releasing a new action.
Here we are introducing this insert
table action in the data control
section.
And let me show you what it does.
When we click on this action,
it opens up a new dialogue and this
dialogue helps us to build and populate
a new table in one place.
So, we have a first section here data
source where I can select what part of
the data set I want to work with. Let's
say sales line.
Here we can choose how many columns we
want for the table. Let's say that we
want three columns or four.
We can delete them.
We can decide to include the header row
or we can remove it.
And we can also toggle this auto select
headline which I will show you in a
second.
Now, I can select which data items I
want to show in my table. Let's say name
customer.
And in this case, I can select a
headline or more conveniently,
I can toggle on auto select and that
work will be done for me.
So, now let's go ahead. Let's choose
another couple of fields.
We can also change the order after the
fact.
And as last thing, I also want to add a
footer
which is outside of the repeater where
I'm going to show the customer bill.
And now all I need to do is to click
click on create table.
And as you can see, I now have a new
table with all the columns,
the header, the repeater and the data
items that I inserted.
Was that it, Mirko? Like was that the
were that the only things we did? Uh
yes, for the word add-in for now. Wow. I
mean, I think this is amazing. I think
this going to help a lot in your design
processes for word layouts and we're not
done yet, so stay tuned in this space.
There will be much more.
Let's switch gears a little bit towards
something that is related to all types
of layouts.
For the last probably three years in
Business Central users were able to
upload their own Excel or Word
even RDL layouts if they want to
through the report layouts page.
And this is great. However,
all layouts uploaded by users are
available on the report request page to
be able to chosen and maybe some of
these layouts are in the like a draft
state. So,
in this release wave we are adding the
ability with a like a life cycle going
from a draft, pending approval, approved
and even retired state. So, how does
that look?
Um here you can see the new if I just go
to the layout status, you can see
different states. No I don't know that
and I'll say that later. This is only
for the user-defined ones, not for the
ones deployed by apps yet.
But um
um if I go to the chart of accounts for
this example, um I actually when I from
the chart of account request page go to
report layouts, I'm as a user, as a
consumer of these layouts, I'm only
presented with the ones that are in
approved state, not the ones that are
draft, retired or under approval. So,
this is a way for you to control as a
layout
administrator which of the layouts are
available to users.
Um the way you set the states is simply
pick one or more layouts here in the
list,
go to layout status and set the the the
state you want to take these into.
And note that this for now only work for
user-defined layouts.
Uh we want to make that also for apps,
but that will not be in the list in this
release wave.
Another feature within document
reporting is that in the application we
have support for language, which means
you can set a language like a document
language on a particular customer to
control the language of their invoices.
However, if you don't set that, but
you're still in a company level
in in a company that deals with multiple
nationalities and multiple nationalities
of customers, so both the people using
Business Central and the ones we are
sending invoices to, we now have a new
way to uh to to have set a company level
default language for document reports
even though they have not the language
have not been set on the customer card.
So, here on company information, you
simply just decide what should be the
default language if something haven't
been set on the on the lower level on
the customer card.
Because
here's just a demo of how the experience
was prior to Business Central
2026 wave one.
Here is
a user who's using the client in English
and on the customer card nothing has
been set on language code.
So, when they send a new sales order,
it is sent in English, which is fine,
except
you get a new employee that is using
Business Central in French.
And
if
if this language has not been set,
whenever that user is sending
a document or an
an invoice, the customer will get it in
the user's language that was using
Business Central, which is
like weird, right? That I'm I'm working
I'm a customer in Denmark and I get a
French invoice. Like
that would be confusing. So,
um instead by setting this default
company language code,
and let's just set it to in this case
American English, then
even though the user is using Business
Central in French, the and even though
the customer card have not specified
English, the company-level default
dictates English and therefore the
customer gets the invoice in English.
Another thing we did was and this is
part of a larger refactoring of all
reports in Business Central. So, if you
follow the AL code for Business Central,
you you will see a lot of refactoring
happening over the next year, but we we
refactored most if not all tool tips on
page level down to tables,
and that will eventually light up in the
report Word add-in as tool tips there.
So, this is just the first of these
refactorings that you will see.
As part of this, we also modernized the
report selection pages in the
application. This is coming in 28.x. So,
we added teaching tips and just aligned
all the caption names and categories.
So, for instance, if you go to tell me
or advanced tell me, you will now have
all these
selection pages look the same, have the
all of them the same category, and have
nice teaching tips that show here on
advanced tell me. And and also if you
open the help pane on any of these
pages.
Like here, you can see the report
selection for page for sales now have a
teaching tip.
And the teaching tips are being used
both in the
report explorer. It's used by Copilot
chat and advanced tell me.
Finally, in this space, we added not
one, not two, but 36 new APIs for
document types so that you can now use
APIs to to in to
to interact with Business Central from
Copilot Studio
or other others to
automations and get not only the five
ones we had before, which was
sales invoice, sales quote, and what
have you, but but now all types of
documents are covered with APIs. There's
a breakout session for that, so go check
that out um
if you want to see more about APIs.
Um
yeah, so sales document types will now
have all these blankets, sales order all
the way to
archive blank order
we'll have these APIs. Same thing in the
purchasing purchasing area from purchase
quotes all the way down to purchase
archived blanket orders.
In inventory, even more from inventory
orders all the way to posted direct
transfer,
you can interact with APIs as well as in
assembly, assembly orders, and posted
assembly orders.
If you want to learn more about this
topic of document reporting, if you go
to aka.ms/BCdeveloper
and navigate down to reporting section,
this is where everything related to Word
add-in and all of these things that you
have seen is is documented there.
If you want to learn more about the API
page
API side of things, aka.ms/BCintegration
takes you to the integration overview
including all the documentation for the
new APIs.
And if you like this content, you might
also like
some of these related sessions, watch
new in server database, Power BI, and
this API session. So, you can find the
links to these in the description of the
video.
And that's it for now. After we say
hello or goodbye,
if you don't know the general resources
of Business Central, stay tuned in the
video. For now, Mirko and I are done. We
hope all the things that we have done in
the space of document reporting and wish
you a great day.
Bye.
>> Bye.
We have compiled a number of general
resources that we believe are key both
for partners, but also Business Central
customers. Most Some of these are
partner, some of them are also for
customers. So, the first one is
called aka.ms/BCall.
This is a partner resource for that
contains lists of every other AKA link
that is needed for you to understand
anything about both the Business Central
product, but also processes around it.
We call these AKA links because they're
called aka.ms and then for forward slash
something. And with Business Central
links, we all always prefix with BC and
then something.
The next one is
our partner network social media for for
Business Central partners, Viva Viva
Engage. So, aka.ms/BCVivaEngage
is where you go and interact with other
partners. It's not open for customers.
So, this is where you can ask questions,
interact with the product group,
interact with
with each other
in a in a closed network.
Second link a third link is for both
partners and customers. We are called
office hours. So, office hours is
something we do once or twice a month
from the product group engaging with the
community about new features or things
we want to discuss. aka.ms/BCOfficeHours
is the is the place where you go to find
out about upcoming events.
These are recorded. I believe the
recordings are available only to
partners, but the live events are
available to customers as well.
Fourth link is YouTube, our YouTube
channel. I'll talk about that
in the next slide and LinkedIn in the
next slide.
And then finally for for Microsoft
partners, the BC's
aka.ms/BCPartnerPortal
is where you get
a lot of the resources as a partner such
as compete decks,
pitch decks, and a lot of other
resources.
For LinkedIn, this is our product
group's LinkedIn profile. We have 30K or
more followers. So, both partners and
customers, this is the place where we
from the product group put in news and
small bits of information outside the
quote unquote official channel. So,
follow us on LinkedIn to learn what's
happening right now
in in this in the around the product.
Um and then
also on our YouTube channel, this is
where you're probably watching this,
aka.ms/BCYouTube.
We put in not only these launch editions
twice a year, but also
Copilot and AI video shorts, tips and
tricks, technical deep dives, under the
hood.
We even have this what's cooking where
we put little nuggets of of videos out
for new features that are even coming in
on the YouTube channel before
they're coming in the release notes. So,
watch
and maybe bookmark us on YouTube. And
also notice all the playlists. So,
the content is also organized in areas,
not only all the videos. So, if you have
an area that has special interest such
as analytics,
you can find an
a playlist and kind of see all the
content related to that.
And that's it. That is truly it. We
won't
There will be no more. So, thank you for
watching all the way to the end.
And again, have a great day. Thank you.